Michael Longley papers, 1960-2000
Emory University
- Writings by Michael Longley, circa 1966-2001, Series 2; Boxes 16-43; OP1-4
  - Prose, Subseries 2.2; Boxes 35-38
    - Whitethorn Hedges [on Patrick Kavanagh] (Box 37, Folder 10)
    - Yeats's Effect on Young Contemporary Poets [W.B. Yeats Summer School lecture, 12 August 1969] (Box 37, Folder 11)
    - Yeats the Tragedian [W.B. Yeats Summer School lecture, 11 August 1970] (Box 37, Folder 12)
    - Untitled [Agnes Broderick] (Box 37, Folder 13)
    - Untitled [Autobiographical] (Box 37, Folder 14)
    - Untitled [Autobiographical] (Box 37, Folder 15)
    - Untitled [Autobiographical] (Box 37, Folder 16)
    - Untitled [Autobiographical] (Box 37, Folder 17)
    - Untitled [Basil Blackshaw] (Box 37, Folder 18)
    - Untitled [BBC Programming] (Box 37, Folder 19)
    - Untitled [Billie Holiday] (Box 37, Folder 20)
    - Untitled [Contemporary Poetry] (Box 37, Folder 21)
    - Untitled [Dalai Lama] (Box 37, Folder 22)
    - Untitled [English Poetry] (Box 37, Folder 23)
    - Untitled [First World War] (Box 37, Folder 24)
    - Untitled [Ian Hamilton Finlay] (Box 37, Folder 25)
    - Untitled [John Hewitt] (Box 37, Folder 26)
    - Untitled [John Hewitt and Northern Ireland] (Box 37, Folder 27)
    - Untitled [Louis MacNeice, John Hewitt, Derek Mahon, Seamus Heaney] (Box 37, Folder 28)
    - Untitled [Louis MacNeice and Section IX of Autumn Journal] (Box 37, Folder 29)
    - Untitled [Derek Mahon, Seamus Heaney, Louis MacNeice] (Box 37, Folder 30)
    - Untitled [Music] (Box 38, Folder 1)
    - Untitled [The Odyssey] (Box 38, Folder 2)
    - Untitled [Patrick Kavanagh] (Box 38, Folder 3)
    - Untitled [Poetry] (Box 38, Folder 4)
    - Untitled [Poetry of Michael Longley] (Box 38, Folder 5)
    - Untitled [Prudence Farmer award speech] (Box 38, Folder 6)
    - Untitled [Robert Graves] (Box 38, Folder 7)
    - Untitled [Seamus Heaney and Nobel prize] (Box 38, Folder 8)
    - Untitled [Stewart Parker] (Box 38, Folder 9)
    - Untitled [Ulster Poetry] (Box 38, Folder 10)
    - Untitled [Ulster Politics] (Box 38, Folder 11)
    - Untitled [Yeats] (Box 38, Folder 12)
    - Untitled [Yeats] (Box 38, Folder 13)
    - Notes for Poetry Readings [undated] (Box 38, Folder 14)
    - Notes on poems and collections (Box 38, Folder 15)
    - Lecture notes and class assignments (Box 38, Folder 16)
    - Lecture notes (Box 38, Folder 17)
    - Jazz-Notes (Box 38, Folder 18)
    - Jazz-Notes (Box 38, Folder 19)
    - Unidentified notes and fragments (Box 38, Folder 20)
    - Unidentified notes and fragments (Box 38, Folder 21)
    - Unidentified notes and fragments (Box 38, Folder 22)
  - Radio and film scripts, 1966-1990, Subseries 2.3; Boxes 39-40
    - "W.B. Yeats," 1966 [reader], TS draft (Box 39, Folder 1)
    - "W.B. Yeats," 1966 [reader], TS draft (Box 39, Folder 2)
    - "W.B. Yeats," 1966 [reader], readers' script (Box 39, Folder 3)
    - "W.B. Yeats," 1966 [reader], readers' script (Box 39, Folder 4)
    - "Over to You: Early in the Morning," 1969 [radio play] (Box 39, Folder 5)
    - "Soundings," January 1970 [conversation between Michael Longley and Maurice Leitch re. Colin Middleton] (Box 39, Folder 6)
    - "Soundings," February 1970 [conversation between Michael Longley and Seamus Heaney re. poetry-reading] (Box 39, Folder 7)
    - "Books, Plays, Poems," by Seamus Heaney, February 1970 [reader; with Seamus Heaney, Derek Mahon, David Hammond] (Box 39, Folder 8)
    - "Books, Plays, Poems: II. Love and Loneliness," by Seamus Heaney, 24 February 1970 [reader; with Seamus Heaney, Derek Mahon, David Hammond] (Box 39, Folder 9)
    - "Books, Plays, Poems: III. Work and Worry," by Seamus Heaney, 24 February 1970 [reader; with Seamus Heaney, Derek Mahon, David Hammond] (Box 39, Folder 10)
    - "Thought for the Day: 'A Favorite Reading,'" September 1970 [re. Patrick Kavanagh] (Box 39, Folder 11)
    - "Today and Yesterday in Northern Ireland: 'Winter,'" November 1970 [radio play] (Box 39, Folder 12)
    - "Thought for the Day," December 1970 [re: "A Nativity"] (Box 39, Folder 13)
    - "New Writing in Ireland," April 1971 [re. Louis MacNeice] (Box 39, Folder 14)
    - "New Writing in Ireland," June 1971 [review of James Simmons' Energy to Burn] (Box 39, Folder 15)
    - "Today and Yesterday in Northern Ireland: The Holidays Ahead," June 1971 [radio play] (Box 39, Folder 16)
    - "Modern Irish History, People and Events: The Great Blight," November 1971 [radio play] (Box 39, Folder 17)
    - "Today and Yesterday in Northern Ireland: J.M. Synge," November 1971 [radio play] (Box 39, Folder 18)
    - "June Review," June 1973 [re. jazz, John Hewitt] (Box 39, Folder 19)
    - "Jack Straw and Beelzbub," December 1977 [radio play] (Box 40, Folder 1)
    - "Today and Yesterday in Northern Ireland: A Story in Sound," January 1978 [radio play] (Box 40, Folder 2)
    - "Ulster in Focus: Bangor," May 1978 (Box 40, Folder 3)
    - "Green Peas & Barley O / Harvest," January 1979 [film script] (Box 40, Folder 4)
    - "Today and Yesterday in Northern Ireland: Story-time: Legend 1," February 1980 (Box 40, Folder 5)
    - "Today and Yesterday in Northern Ireland, Story-time: Legend 2 'Oisin in the Land of Youth,'" February 1980 (Box 40, Folder 6)
    - "Ulster in Focus: The Light Behind the Rain," March 1982 (Box 40, Folder 7)
    - "Explorations II," February 1986 (Box 40, Folder 8)
    - "Thought for the Day" talks, October 1986 [six scripts] (Box 40, Folder 9)
    - "The Poet's Eye," May 1987 (Box 40, Folder 10)
    - "Explorations: A Poet at Work," March 1988 (Box 40, Folder 11)
    - "Poets in Person: Michael Longley," June 1988 [reading] (Box 40, Folder 12)
    - "The Corner of the Eye," 1988 (Box 40, Folder 13)
    - "Words of Faith," February 1990 [re. The Odyssey] (Box 40, Folder 14)
    - "BBC Notes on Radio Drama," 1973 (Box 40, Folder 15)
    - Undated film and radio scripts
    - "The Battle of Mag Mucrime," [with source material], by Michael Longley (Box 40, Folder 16)
    - ["Today and Yesterday in Northern Ireland: The Death of Muircertach Mac Erca"], [radio script] (Box 40, Folder 17)
    - "Dr. Johnson's Journey to the Hebrides," by Michael Longley, [radio script?] (Box 40, Folder 18)
    - "Doctor Jazz," by Michael Longley, [radio script] (Box 40, Folder 19)
    - "Gallery--Michael Longley" (Box 40, Folder 20)
    - "Poets on Poetry," by Michael Longley (Box 40, Folder 21)
    - "Three Love Poems II," by Michael Longley (Box 40, Folder 22)
    - Unidentified script (Box 40, Folder 23)
    - Unidentified script, by Michael Longley [fragment] (Box 40, Folder 24)
    - Unidentified script [re: poets of Northern Ireland] (Box 40, Folder 25)
    - Unidentified script (Box 40, Folder 26)
    - Unidentified script, by Michael Longley [re: his poetry] (Box 40, Folder 27)
  - Works edited by Michael Longley, 1988-2001, Subseries 2.4; Boxes 41-42
    - Louis MacNeice: Selected Poems (1988), notes and proposed selections (Box 41, Folder 1)
    - Louis MacNeice: Selected Poems (1988), early annotated proof (Box 41, Folder 2)
    - Louis MacNeice: Selected Poems (1988), Introduction, MS (Box 41, Folder 3)
    - Louis MacNeice: Selected Poems (1988), Preface and Introduction, TS (Box 41, Folder 4)
    - Louis MacNeice: Selected Poems (1988), mock-up (Box 41, Folder 5)
    - Louis MacNeice: Selected Poems (1988), mock-up (Box 41, Folder 6)
    - Louis MacNeice: Selected Poems (1988), annotated galley proofs (Box 41, Folder 7)
    - Poems: W. R. Rodgers (1993), TS drafts of introduction (Box 41, Folder 8)
    - Poems: W. R. Rodgers (1993), associated correspondence (Box 41, Folder 9)
    - Poems: W. R. Rodgers (1993), proofs (Box 41, Folder 10)
    - Poems: W. R. Rodgers (1993), proofs from Gallery Press (Box 42, Folder 1)
    - Poetry Ireland Review 50 (Summer 1996), TS drafts of introduction (Box 42, Folder 2)
    - Poetry Ireland Review 50 (Summer 1996), draft of contents (Box 42, Folder 3)
    - Poetry Ireland Review 50 (Summer 1996), submissions and associated correspondence (Box 42, Folder 4)
    - Poetry Ireland Review 50 (Summer 1996), submissions and associated correspondence (Box 42, Folder 5)
    - Louis MacNeice: Poems (2001), TS drafts of introduction (Box 42, Folder 6)
    - Louis MacNeice: Poems (2001), galley proof (Box 42, Folder 7)
  - Interviews with Michael Longley, circa 1980-2001, Subseries 2.5; Box 43: folders 1-8
    - [Untitled], with Siobhan McSweeney, circa 1980 (Box 43, Folder 1)
    - With Dillon Johnstone, circa 1986 [ Irish Literary Supplement, Fall 1986] (Box 43, Folder 2)
    - With Dermot Healy, circa 1994? [ Force Ten, Southern Review Summer 1995] (Box 43, Folder 3)
    - With Sarah Broom, April 1997 (Box 43, Folder 4)
    - With Peter McDonald, circa 1998 (Box 43, Folder 5)
    - With Andrew Morrison, January 1999 [ Matrix] (Box 43, Folder 6)
    - With unknown, circa 2000 (Box 43, Folder 7)
    - With "MM," circa 2001 (Box 43, Folder 8)
  - Notebooks, Subseries 2.6; Box 43: folder 10
    - Notebooks [include drafts of "A Touch," "A Sprig of Bay," "Foam," "Rain and Grace," "The Fireflies"] (Box 43, Folder 9)
- Writings by others, Series 3; Boxes 44-48; OP 5-7
  The Michael Longley papers include numerous poems and prose works in manuscript or typescript form by other contemporary writers. Particularly well-represented are both Seamus Heaney and Derek Mahon. When a manuscript was included as an enclosure with a letter, it has been filed with that letter in Series 1. See also Series 8, Belfast Group sheets.
  Subseries 3.3 includes prose works and drama, as well as radio scripts, screenplays, and some artwork.
  Organized into three subseries: (3.1) Poetry, (3.2) Essays on Michael Longley, and (3.3) Other writings.
  - Poetry, Subseries 3.1; Boxes 44-46: folders 1-4; OP5
    - Adcock, Fleur: "Bodnath," "A Day in October," "External Service,," "Flying Back," "Midnight Call," "Naxal," The Scenic Route, contents page; "Pupation," Untitled ["The hailstorm was in my head"], Untitled ["Abandoning all my principles"], Untitled ["Their new puppy chases buffaloes"] (Box 44, Folder 1)
    - Boland, Eavan: "Chardin's 'Back From the Market'," "The Botanic Gardens," "Conversation with an Inspector of Taxes about Poetry," "Mirages," "Migration," "The Poets," "The Pilgrim," "Requiem for a Personal Friend," "Shakespeare," "After the Deluge," "The Time He Changed," "The War Horse," "Anon.," "For Naoise at Four," "Sisters," "Cyclist with Cut Branches," "Fons Bandusiae," "Yeats in Civil War" (Box 44, Folder 2)
    - Carson, Ciaran: "The Patchwork Quilt," "Snow," "Smithfield" [x2] (Box 44, Folder 3)
    - Carson, Ciaran: Belfast Confetti, typescript [photocopy] (Box 44, Folder 4)
    - Carson, Douglas, "In Memoriam J.M.M.," "In Memoriam Sam Hanna Bell," "Barbour Ward" (Box 44, Folder 5)
    - Dhomhnaill, Nuala Ní: "Fear," "An Sceach Gheal," "Man / Sex Object," "Titim I ngrá," "From the Plague Journal," "The Three Musicians," "Santa Lucia's First Communion," "Dán Baeg an Earriaigh Bhig" (Box 44, Folder 6)
    - Dunn, Douglas: "The City," "The Apple Tree" (Box 44, Folder 7)
    - Enright, D.J.: "The Question of Lust," "Midstream," "What the Martian learnt from the Underground" (Box 44, Folder 8)
    - Fenton, James: Children in Exile TS (Box 44, Folder 9)
    - Harrison, Tony: "The Act" (Box 44, Folder 10)
    - Heaney, Seamus: "Servant Boy," "Incertus," "The Grauballe Man," Untitled ["This evening the cuckoo and the corncrake"], "At a Potato Digging," "The Schoolbag" [x2], "In Memoriam Francis Ledwidge," "A Casualty," "A Postcard from North Antrim," "Leavings," "A Drink of Water," "The Other Sort," "The Backward Look," "A New Song," "Bog Queen," "Kinship," "Ugolino," "Exposure," "Thaw," "Poet's Twilight," "Prelude in Glanmore," "The Poet Crowned," "The Train," "Remembering Forecasts," "A Dream of Jealousy," "A Pillowed Head," "Glanmore Revisited" ["1. Lustral Sonnet," "2. Scrabble," "3. Scene Shifts," "4. 1973."], "Resin," "The Settle Bed," From Lightenings, "4. Squarings," "Casting and Gathering," "Man and Boy," "Wheels within Wheels," "Seeing Things," "The Golden Bough," "The Ash Plant," "The Pitchfork," "Scrabble," "Undine," "The Given Note," "The Wife's Tale," "Dawn," "The Last Mummer," "Medallion," "Moving In," "First Calf," "The Barn," "Trout," "Waterfall," "The Perch," "The Bookcase," "The Thatcher," "Orchard Song," "The Other Side" [fragment] (Box 44, Folder 11)
    - Heaney, Seamus: Door Into the Dark, proofs (Box 44, Folder 12)
    - Heaney, Seamus: Wintering Out, early TS (Box 44, Folder 13)
    - Heaney, Seamus: Wintering Out, TS (Box 44, Folder 14)
    - Hobsbaum, Philip: "Up Shit Creek" (Box 44, Folder 15)
    - Hughes, Glyn: "Age" (Box 44, Folder 16)
    - Jamie, Kathleen: Jizzen TS (Box 44, Folder 17)
    - Kennelly, Brendan: "Woman in a doorway," "To imitate the sun," "The Adventure of Learning" [photocopy] (Box 44, Folder 18)
    - [Longley, Michael]: translations by Christine Pagnoulle, "Blessures," Kindertotenlieder," "Le Papillon Blanc," "L'industrie du lin," "En quittant Inishmore" (Box 44, Folder 19)
    - McGuckian, Medbh: On Ballycastle Beach, typescript [photocopy] (Box 44, Folder 20)
    - MacIntyre, Tom: "Connemara," "Swift to Vanessa," "Aisling," "Father," "Excursion to Emhain Macha," "Drumlin Prayer" (Box 44, Folder 21)
    - Mahon, Derek: "Between High Tide and Low," "Consolations of Philosophy," "A Dying Art," "Homecoming," "Some Day," "Resurrection," "Legacies," "The Graduate in Metal Box," "Suburban Walk," "The Snow Party," "Kreutzer Sonata," "Man and Bird," "The Poets," "Book Ends," "In Carrowdore Churchyard," "Recalling Aran" [x2], "Canadian Pacific" [x2], "Design for a Grecian Urn," The Joycentenary Ode," "My Wicked Uncle" [x2], "An Unborn Child,""Glengormley," "In Retirement," Untitled ["Now that the postal strike is over"], "The OutsideWorld," "Epitaph for an Old Fascist," "Epitaph for Robert J. Flaherty," "A Disused Shed in Co. Wexford," Goodbye to the Trees," "C.P. Cavafy's Alexandria," "Four Versions of Cavafy," "The Charles River in January" [x2], "Opening Time" [with "Design for a Grecian Urn"], "Preface to a Love Poem," "A Refusal to Mourn," Autobiographies ["1. The Home Front," "2. The Lost Girls," "3. The Last Resort," "4. The Bicycle"], "Toronto," "Exit Molloy," "Fire-King," "Ovid in Tomis," "The Andean Flute," "The Dawn Chorus," "The Woods," "Beyond Howth Head," "The Poets Lie where they Fell," "At Swift's Hospital," "The World Is Everything That is the Case," "Rathlin Island," "The Snow Party," list of poems; "Epigram" ["Between High Tide and Low"], "1 Corinthians 13," "What will Remain," "In Woburn Walk," "Leisure American Style," Gramsci's Ashes; Untitled ["These bright directions you have lost"] (Box 44, Folder 22)
    - Mahon, Derek: The Chimeras (Box 44, Folder 23)
    - Mahon, Derek: High Time with ALS, 31 July 1984 (Box 45, Folder 1)
    - Mahon, Derek: Hunt By Night, original typescript with holograph corrections by Derek Mahon (Box 45, Folder 2)
    - Meehan, Paula: "It is all I ever wanted" (Box 45, Folder 3)
    - Montague, John: "Outside Armagh Jail," "Sunny Jim" (Box 45, Folder 4)
    - Muldoon, Paul: "Immram" [x2], "From Strength to Strength," "The High Chair," "Beaver," "The Bald Patch," "A Trifle," "The Hands," "Blewits," "Mary Farl Powers Pink Spotted Torso," "Big Foot," "Aftermath," "The Frog," "Love Poem," "Yellow Ragwort," "The Earthquake," "Bridal," "Lord Hawhaw," "Gifts," "Fix," "Making the Move," "Mushrooms," "Mink," "Sky-Woman," "Emily," "Edward Kienholz The State Hospital," "Glanders," "The Destroying Angel," "Rabies," "The Fox," Untitled ["The Great Auk and the Little Auk"], "Wolves," "Bears," "Emily," "Pandas," "Anthrax," "The Wishbone," "Caprice des Dieux," "Sylvia," "Toxophilus," "Other Women," "Tibet," "Excitable Boy," "Early Warning," "International Departures," "from The Hopewell Haiku" ["Good Friday.. ."] (Box 45, Folder 5)
    - Muldoon, Paul: Quoof, typescript (Box 45, Folder 6)
    - O'Driscoll, Dennis: "Song," "Halloween," "Home," "The Cow" (Box 45, Folder 7)
    - Ormsby, Frank: "The Kensico Dam," "Deadlock," "The Earthquake," "On Not Hearing the American Nightjar," "Small World," "Fireflies," "Colin Middleton: 'Lagan, Annadale'" (Box 45, Folder 8)
    - Ormsby, Frank: ed. The Hip Flask, photocopied proofs (Box 45, Folder 9)
    - Raine, Craig: "A Walk in the Country," photocopied proof with MS note from Raine (Box OP5)
    - Raine, Craig: "Words on the Page" (Box 45, Folder 10)
    - Simmons, James: "Poor Tom," "Intruder on Station Island" (Box 45, Folder 11)
    - Tinley, Bill: "Casualty" (Box 45, Folder 12)
    - Unidentified poems by others (Box 45, Folder 13)
    - A Life's Span, TS of Irish poetry reading / anthology (Box 45, Folder 14)
    - Collected mimeographed poems by others (Box 45, Folder 15)
    - Other poems (Box 45, Folder 16)
    - Other poems (Box 46, Folder 1)
    - Other poems (Box 46, Folder 2)
    - Translations (French) of Michael Longley's poetry by unknown (Box 46, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous poetry forwarded to Michael Longley by Douglas Carson (Box 46, Folder 4)
  - Essays on Michael Longley, Subseries 3.2; Box 46: folders 5-16 - Box 47: folder 1-4
    - Allen, Michael, "Louis MacNeice and Michael Longley: Some Examples of Affinity and Influence" (Box 46, Folder 5)
    - Allen, Michael, "Rhythm and Development in Longley's Earlier Poetry" (Box 46, Folder 6)
    - Brearton, Fran, "Michael Longley: Poet in No Man's Land" (Box 46, Folder 7)
    - Drummond, Gavin, "Derek Mahon and Michael Longley: Competition, Collaboration and Censorship" (Box 46, Folder 8)
    - Greacen, Robert, Review of Echo Gate (Box 46, Folder 9)
    - Longley, Becky, "A Poet, And I Know It" (Box 46, Folder 10)
    - McCue, Jim, Review of Poems, 1963-1983 (Box 46, Folder 11)
    - McDonald, Peter, "Michael Longley's Homes" (Box 46, Folder 12)
    - Managan, Peter, The Poetry of Michael Longley: An Assessment (Box 46, Folder 13)
    - Peacock, Alan, "'How do you sew the night?': The Weather in Japan'" ["'Eros and Thanatos': The Weather in Japan'"] (Box 46, Folder 14)
    - Peacock, Alan, "Introduction" to The Poetry of Michael Longley (Box 46, Folder 15)
    - Peacock, Alan, "Michael Longley: Poet Between Worlds" (Box 46, Folder 16)
    - Picciotto, Daniela, Michael Longley ed i Poeti Nord-Irlandesi [dissertation] (Box 47, Folder 1)
    - Robben, Bernhard, "Vom Erfinden der Geschichte" (Box 47, Folder 2)
    - Storey, Mark, "Michael Longley: the nightingale's throat, the vocal chords of the orang-outang" (Box 47, Folder 3)
    - Unidentified, Introduction for Michael Longley, 25 April 2000 (Box 47, Folder 4)
  - Other writings, Subseries 3.3; Box 47: folders 5-48 - Box 48; OP 6-7
    - Bell, Sam Hanna, "Modern Irish History, People and Events: Wood's Ha'Pence" [radio script] (Box 47, Folder 5)
    - Boitano, Piero?, "Joyce and After: Mythical Shadows of the Irish Ulysses" (Box 47, Folder 6)
    - Boyle, John, "Bird Alone: Irish Prose Fiction since James Joyce" (Box 47, Folder 7)
    - Brennan, Mark, "Sarah" [script] (Box 47, Folder 8)
    - Carson, Ciaran, "Belfast Notes" (Box OP6)
    - Carson, Douglas, "Modern Irish History, People and Events: The Clare Election," [radio script] (Box 47, Folder 9)
    - Carson, Douglas, "Modern Irish History, People and Events: Covenant Day," [radio script] (Box 47, Folder 10)
    - Dawe, Gerald, review of Ireland and the English Crisis by Tom Paulin (Box 47, Folder 11)
    - Glendinning, Robin, "Letter from Ulster," [radio script] (Box 47, Folder 12)
    - Glendinning, Robin, "The Man in Black" [script] (Box 47, Folder 13)
    - Gorman, Damian, "My Da, Your Da" [script] (Box 47, Folder 14)
    - Heaney, Seamus, "Exploration" [radio script] (Box 47, Folder 15)
    - Heaney, Seamus, "Here in Ulster: 'Everyman'" [radio script] (Box 47, Folder 16)
    - Heaney, Seamus, "People at Work: 'Poet'" [radio script] (Box 47, Folder 17)
    - Heaney, Seamus, "The Sense of the Past" [lecture; x2] (Box 47, Folder 18)
    - Heaney, Seamus, "Shifting an Emphasis: the lyric poetry of Robert Frost" (Box 47, Folder 19)
    - [Heaney, Seamus], "The Two Voices of 'Ploughman'" (Box 47, Folder 20)
    - Hobsbaum, Philip, "The Critics at the Harmonium: Blackmur and Winters on Stevens" (Box 47, Folder 21)
    - Johnston, Jennifer, "The Names" [radio script] (Box 47, Folder 22)
    - Kavanagh, Patrick, The Great Hunger [script by Tom MacIntyre] (Box 47, Folder 23)
    - Leonard, Tom, "The Moment of Innocence, and the Moment of Experience: The Poetry of Thomas O'Brien" (Box 47, Folder 24)
    - Lewis, Helen, untitled [autobiographical] (Box 47, Folder 25)
    - McCaughan, Michael, "Displayed in Mortal Light" [photography; with an introduction by Michael Longley] (Box 47, Folder 26)
    - McGahern, John, "The Stoat" (Box 47, Folder 27)
    - [McGuckian, Medbh], "Thought for the Day: Medbh McGuckian," [three radio scripts] (Box 47, Folder 28)
    - McGuinness, Frank, "Caoin: A Song for Nine Voices" [script] (Box 48, Folder 1)
    - Mahon, Derek, "A Ghostly Rumble Among the Drums" [photocopy] (Box 48, Folder 2)
    - Mahon, Derek, "Patrick Kavanagh" (Box 48, Folder 3)
    - Mahon, Derek, "A View from the Long Grass" (Box 48, Folder 4)
    - Martin, Angus, "Dead Ringers" (Box 48, Folder 5)
    - Mathews, Aidan, "Trojans" [script] (Box 48, Folder 6)
    - Morgan, Jeffrey, "A short note of apology for being a portraitist" (Box 48, Folder 7)
    - Newson, George, music for "My Dancing Days Are Over," "Songs of Love," and "From The New Divan" (Box OP7)
    - Parker, Stewart, "Dramatis Personae" [John Malone Memorial Lecture] (Box 48, Folder 8)
    - Pinder, R. F., "A Briton as a Nazi Slave" (Box 48, Folder 9)
    - Pirrie, Jill, Pushkin Prizes talk 15 November 1997 (Box 48, Folder 10)
    - Robb, John, The Departitioning of Ulster (Box 48, Folder 11)
    - Rodgers, W.R., "Memorandum on Literature and Writers in Northern Ireland" (Box 48, Folder 12)
    - Sutcliff, Rosemary, "Modern Irish History, People and Events: The Hanging of Henry Joy," [radio script] (Box 48, Folder 13)
    - Sutcliff, Rosemary, "Today and Yesterday in Northern Ireland: 'The Children of Lir,'" [radio script] (Box 48, Folder 14)
    - Sweeney, Matthew, "Children's Poet" (Box 48, Folder 15)
    - Tannahill, Anne, "Blackstaff Press: Publishing 'A Local Row'" (Box 48, Folder 16)
    - [Unidentified], "Causeway," [radio script] (Box 48, Folder 17)
    - [Unidentified], "Education: The Poets' Picture" (Box 48, Folder 18)
    - [Unidentified], "January" [chapter] (Box 48, Folder 19)
    - [Unidentified], "Joyce Cary- The Writer and His Theme, by Barbara Fisher" (Box 48, Folder 20)
    - [Unidentified], "The Locked Door" (Box 48, Folder 21)
    - [Unidentified], "The Poetry of Francis Ledwidge" (Box 48, Folder 22)
    - [Unidentified], "Schoolboy" [film script] (Box 48, Folder 23)
    - [Unidentified], incomplete script (Box 48, Folder 24)
    - Miscellaneous Writings by Others (Box 48, Folder 25)
    - Prose forwarded to Michael Longley by Douglas Carson (Box 48, Folder 26)
    - Unidentified fragments (Box 48, Folder 27)
- Printed material, 1952-2000, Series 4; Boxes 49-56; OP 8-12
  Series 4 includes assorted printed material, including clippings, reviews, and promotional material for Michael Longley's own books and readings. Subseries 4.1 consists of printed material by Longley. Most are poems unless otherwise marked in brackets.
  Subseries 4.2 contains reviews and promotional material concerning Longley's writings, as well as newspaper clippings which mention Longley, and longer pieces which involve the writer more centrally.
  The bulk of Subseries 4.3 has been divided into three main categories: printed material with a literary subject, printed material concerning the Arts (particularly painting), and any other printed material.